Guide to the Edward Allworth papers, 1944-2000 [bulk 1969-1992]
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Edward Allworth papers
1944-2000
1969-1992
3621
b17032772
MssCol 3621
Allworth, Edward.
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
8.3 linear feet 21 boxes 679 kb (11 computer files) 19 audio files
Edward A. Allworth is professor emeritus of Turco-Soviet Studies in the Middle Eastern and Asian Languages and Cultures Department of Columbia University. He began his career at Columbia in 1961, dedicating his writings and teaching to the study of ethnic minority populations in Soviet Central Asia. Professor Allworth's papers include research documents focusing on Crimean Tatars, Uzbeks, Tajiks and Bukharan Jews, and the Soviet war in Afghanistan. Materials consist of correspondence, manuscripts, research files and statistical analysis, photographs, oral history recordings and biographical scrapbooks, printed matter and a small amount of personal miscellany.
Edward Alfred Allworth, professor emeritus of Turco-Soviet Studies in the Middle Eastern and Asian Languages and Cultures Department at Columbia University, is a specialist on ethnic minority populations in former Soviet Central Asia. He was born December 1, 1920, the son of Edward and Ethel (Walker) Allworth. He received his bachelor's degree from Oregon State University, followed by a master's from the University of Chicago, and a Ph.D. from Columbia University. After working at both Reed College and the Ford Foundation, Professor Allworth returned to Columbia, where he would spend the majority of his professional career focusing on Central Asia.
Allworth was director of the Program on Soviet Nationality Problems beginning in 1970, head of the Center for the Study of Central Asia, and general editor of the Central Asia Book Series beginning in 1983. Among his numerous works as an author and editor were: Central Asian Publishing and the Rise of Nationalism; The Modern Uzbeks: from the fourteenth century to the present; Uzbek Literary Politics; The Nationality Question in Soviet Central Asia; and Nationality Group Survival in Multiethnic States.
This collection was transferred from the Asian and Middle Eastern Division of The New York Public Library in 2001.
Edward Allworth's papers, spanning 1944 to 1994, document his interest in and research on ethnic minority groups and the question of nationality in Soviet Central Asia and on the Soviet conflict in Afghanistan. Populations represented in the collection are Crimean Tatars, Uzbeks, Tajiks and Bukharan Jews.
The collection is arranged by ethnic group. Materials consist of correspondence, manuscripts, research files and statistical analysis, photographs, oral history and interview recordings, biographical scrapbooks, printed matter, and artifacts.
The Afghan files contain newspaper clippings and other printed matter on the Soviet conflict, and Arabic manuscripts of unknown date, obtained by Professor Allworth from a dealer operating in the country.
Items related to Crimean Tatars focus on their experiences of deportation to Central Asia in 1944, activist movements beginning in the 1960s, and their push for the right of return to the Crimea in the 1980s. A significant amount of material was received from activist and author Reshat Djemilev, including an extensive oral history, in Russian.
The Uzbek materials consist of the "Uzbek Intelligentsia Project," which looked at the integration of ethnic Uzbeks into the Uzbek Soviet and larger USSR Supreme Soviet. These materials consist of selected research files compiled on members of both Soviets, and statistical printouts analyzing Allworth's collected data. There are also files related to Allworth's translation work of Abdalfauf Fitrat.
The Tajik section of documents, the smallest in the collection, consists of writings by Mordekhay Bachaev; interviews in Hebrew of members of the small ethnic and religious minority of Bukharan Jews; newspaper clippings on the resurgence of a Muslim identity in Dushanbe following the fall of the Soviet Union; and other printed matter.
In Arabic, Crimean Tatar, English, French, German, Hebrew, Polish, Pushto, Russian, Tajik and Uzbek. Although much of the collection consists of materials using the Latin alphabet, many texts are present with the Arabic and Cyrillic alphabet. There is also one example of a Tajik language document represented in both Cyrillic and Hebrew (Ghazaliet in box 7).
Donated by Edward Allworth, 1994.
Aimaq, Faizullah; Dzhemilev, Reshat; Eckmann, János; Fitrat, 1886-1938; Muḣib, 1911-; Crimean Tatars -- Civil rights -- Soviet Union; Jews, Bukharan; Minorities -- Soviet Union; Nationalism -- Asia, Central; Tajiks; Uzbeks; interviews; memoirs; photographs; Scrapbooks; sound recordings; Afghanistan -- History -- Soviet occupation, 1979-1989; Soviet Union -- Ethnic relations; Uzbekistan; College teachers -- United States
- Series I. Afghanistan files, 1977-1993; 112720; 1 box
  The Afghanistan files do not focus on a particular ethnic group. Rather, they are a small collection of disparate materials about, and from, that country. The files consist of manuscripts in Arabic and Cyrillic script, correspondence related to their provenance, transcripts of an interview with author Faizullah Aimaq on Kabul radio, and collected printed matter on Afghanistan.
  The older manuscripts are of unknown date, and several appear to have been purchased through a manuscripts dealer working with sources in Afghanistan. Related correspondence indicates two of the documents are in Arabic, and one in an unidentified language thought to be similar to the Chaghatay language spoken by Chinese Turkestanis.
  The transcript (in Uzbek, written in Cyrillic) of a 1976 radio interview with Faizullah Aimaq is located in box 1, folder 2. It is also available as digital sound files; see Series VI).
  Also included amongst the Afghan materials are several folders of printed matter, consisting of various article clippings on Afghanistan, a 1981 copy of the Pushto language newspaper Zeray, and newspaper clippings on the Soviet-Afghan conflict.
  In Arabic, English, Pushto and Uzbek.
  - Arabic manuscripts and related correspondence, 1980-1982; 112721 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts and notes, 112723 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Printed matter and written summaries of articles, 1978-1988; 112724 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Zeray, 1981; 112725 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1977-1993; 112726 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
- Series II. Crimean Tatar files, 1944-1994; 112727; 4 boxes
  The Crimean Tatar files focus on members of this ethnic group's 1944 deportation under Stalin's order to Central Asia, and their efforts, beginning in the 1960s, to obtain the right of return. Allworth's support for Crimean Tatar activism is documented in this collection of materials, as are his efforts to record deportees' personal experiences. Among the items present are correspondence and photographs; manuscripts, autobiographies and diaries; a recorded oral history; Allworth's own research and writings; and papers from the Ismail Gaspirali Fund at Columbia University.
  Correspondence consists of letters regarding research, Allworth's attempts to assist in publishing a samizdat manuscript, general exchanges with contacts in the Soviet Union, information on Reshat Djemilev and Mustapha Cemilev, publications from the Organization of Crimean Tatars Nationalist Movement, and photographs of Crimean Tatar protests in the Soviet Union in 1988.
  Among the manuscripts included is a photocopy of the samizdat text of the Tashkent Trial, a 1969 trial of Crimean Tatar dissidents which galvanized the Tatar population in the USSR and abroad. Also included are a biographical scrapbook on Eskender Ganeevich Umerov, manuscripts of Reshat Djemilev's Reflections and Short Analysis of Events During the Moscow Summer, and miscellaneous documents and photographs obtained from Djemilev. See Series VI for a lengthy oral history given by Djemilev in Russian.
  Following the manuscripts are a number of notebooks of unknown provenance on various Crimean Tatar topics. These appear to be different from Allworth's own research and writing files, which focus on the growing national identity movement, Soviet policy towards the ethnic group, and the question of a Crimean Tatar "historical memory." These notebooks include materials in a number of languages, including Crimean Tatar.
  The Crimean Tatar materials also contain papers related to the Ismail Gaspirali Fund. The fund, founded by Tatars in New York City, was established to make a small donation to Columbia University's Center for the Study of Central Asia for the purpose of obtaining and translating materials on current affairs in the region.
  In Crimean Tatar, English, French, German, Polish and Russian.
  - Correspondence, 1963-1994; 112728 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Writings and conferences, 1984-1990; 112729 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ismail Gaspirali Fund and lecture, 1984 Sept; 112730 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript of the Tashkent Trial and other documents, ca. 1969; 112731 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Biographical scrapbook of Eskender Ganeevich Umerov, 112732 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Reshat Djemilev materials, 112733
    - Reflections, 1977; 112734 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Short Analysis of Events During the Moscow Summer, 1987; 112735 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous documents and photographs, 1987-1989; 112736 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Notebooks 1-2, 112737 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notebooks 3-8, 112738 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Notebook 9, 112739 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - Newsletter Avdet, 1990-1993; 112740 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1967-1993; 112741 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Articles and reports for research, 1944-1993; 112742 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - Maps, prints and photographs, 1985; 112743 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series III. Tajik files, 1967-1993; 112744; 1.5 boxes
  The Tajik files consist of photocopies of writings by Mordekhay Bachaev, manuscripts of interviews with Bukharan Jews, and newspaper clippings and other miscellaneous printed matter.
  The manuscript memoir by Mordekhay Bachaev, also known as 'Muhib,' consists of photocopies of handwritten pages in Tajik, written in Cyrillic, covering his life from 1920 to 1939. Also included with his writings is a Tajik-language publication, entitled Ghazaliet, written in Hebrew and Cyrillic scripts.
  The documents related to Bukharan Jews, which were originally arranged with the Tajik materials, consist of Hebrew manuscripts of interviews about the Jewish community in Bukhara prior to and following Soviet rule, paired with English-language summaries of these interviews.
  The miscellaneous printed matter pertains to the resurgence of a Muslim identity in the city of Dushanbe following the fall of the Soviet Union, and miscellaneous printed matter related to Bukharan Jews.
  In English, Hebrew, Russian and Tajik.
  - M. Bachaev Vospominaniya, 112745
    - Table of Contents, ca. 1970; 112746 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript on 1920-1935, ca. 1970; 112747 (Box 6, Folder 2-7)
    - Manuscript on 1922-1923, ca. 1970; 112748 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript on 1936-1939, ca. 1970; 112749 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Gazaliet (in Cyrillic and Hebrew scripts), 1978; 112750 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Interviews with Bukharan Jews (in Hebrew), 1967-1969; 112751 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Miscellany related to Bukharan Jews, 1974, 1987; 112752 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1988-1993; 112753 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1983, 1992; 112754 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series IV. Uzbek and Supreme Soviet project research files, 1970-2000; 112755; 11 computer files 5 boxes; 679 Kilobytes
  Allworth's materials related to Uzbeks and Uzbekistan stem from his project analyzing ethnic minority participation in the Supreme Soviet. The project was alternately referred to in his notes as the "Uzbek Intelligentsia Project."
  The project analyzed Uzbek influence in the USSR through an examination of Uzbek members of the Supreme Soviet, compared with those in the Uzbek Soviet. Materials consist of selected "data sheets" on each member, statistical reports labeled "cross-tabulations" and "frequencies," project management materials, and other miscellany.
  The "cross-tabulations" look at factors such as education, rural vs. urban origin, gender, locality (oblast, krai, etc.), and former employment. Also included are comparisons of Uzbek members with Azerbaijanis and Tajiks, and comparisons across gender, by birth year, committee, and doctorate vs. candidate degrees.
  Also present in this series are essays, drafts, research notes, and professional correspondence related to Allworth’s translation work and research on Uzbek literature and history, which focuses heavily on the writer and theorist Abdalrauf Fitrat. The Fitrat texts included in the collection are Bidil, Qiyamät, Satan’s Mutiny Against the Lord, and The Judgment Day. Some of the translation work was funded by an NEH grant, and includes Allworth’s progress reports on the project.
  There is also an index to the Turki journal, Ayina, which was published from 1913 to 1915 and edited by Mahmud Khoja Behbudiy. This chronological index was compiled by Allworth and his graduate assistants, and contains extensive annotations.
  In English, Uzbek, French, Tajik, and Turkish. The Uzbek materials are mostly printed in Cyrillic script, with some texts also in Arabic script.
  - Project management materials, 1975-1979; 112756 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Key to codes for data sheets, projects 1 and 2, ca. 1975; 112757 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Inventory of tables, ca. 1978; 112758 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Preliminary variable and value lists, ca. 1975; 112759 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Deputies of the Supreme Soviet, 8th Assembly, letter A, 1970; 112760 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Data sheets: Non-Uzbek delegates from Uzbekistan, 1974; 112761 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Data sheets: letter A, 112762 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Uzbek intelligentsia project management, 112763 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Uzbek consumer goods production statistics, by oblast, 1940-1970, ca. 1978; 112764 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Azerbaijani SSR elections report, 1990; 112765 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Uzbek intelligentsia project, cross-tabulations, 112766
    - General #1-12b, 1977-1978; 112767 (Box 10, Folder 2-5)
    - Uzbek vs. Azerbaijani #C1, 1978; 112768 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - General #C2, 1978; 112769 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Uzbek vs. Azerbaijani #C3-C9, 1978; 112770 (Box 11, Folder 3-5)
    - Male vs. female #C10, 112771 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - By republic #C11, 112772 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - By committee #C12, 112773 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - By birth year and rural/urban #C13, 112774 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - By oblast, 1978; 112775 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 'Uzbek 50 (SS)', 1978; 112776 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Uzbeks vs. Tajiks, 1980; 112777 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Nationality, by employer type, 1980; 112778 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Doctorate degrees, Uzbeks vs. other Central Asians, 1980; 112779 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Candidate and doctorate degrees, all nationalities, 1980; 112780 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Uzbek intelligentsia project, Frequencies, 112781
    - General #1,3 and unnumbered, 1977; 112782 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - General, 1980; 112783 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Crosstabulations and frequencies, 1980; 112784 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Other statistical analysis, 1978-1980; 112785 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Fitrat Research and Translations, 2051134
    - Annotated Bibliography, Footnotes, and Preface, 1995-2000; 2051271; er.2; 292.4 Kilobytes (3 computer files)
    - Article Drafts, 1984-1989; 2051135; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Article Drafts and Notes, 1992-1994; 2051136; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Article Drafts, 1996; 2051137; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Article Drafts - Eurasian Studies Yearbook, 1992-1996; 2051138; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Draft Translations and Correspondence, 1978; 2051139; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Monograph - Qiyamät and Satan’s Mutiny, 1994-1998; 2051140; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - NEH Grant Reports and Translation Drafts, 1990-1991; 2051141; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Notes and Research, 1991-1997; 2051142; 33433116987565 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Notes from and about Fitrat, 2051144; 33433116987573 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Notes, Research, and Correspondence, 1994-1998; 2051145; 33433116987573 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Research Materials, 1991; 2051146; 33433116987573 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Bidil, 2051213
      - Notes, 1994-1997; 2051214; 33433116987573 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Translation Notes and Correspondence, 1993-1996; 2051216; 33433116987573 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Research and Notes, 2051217; 33433116987573 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Rough Drafts, 1993; 2051218; 33433116987573 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Translation Drafts, 2051219; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Translation Notes, 1993-1998; 2051220; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Translation Notes and Correspondence, 1993-1998; 2051221; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - The Judgment Day, 2051222
      - Draft Translation and Notes, 2051223; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Translation Annotations, 2051263; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Qiyamät, 2051264
      - Translation Notes and Correspondence, 1992; 2051265; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Translation Notes, 2051266; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Translation Notes, 1989; 2051267; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Satan’s Mutiny Against the Lord, 2051182
      - Translation Notes and Annotations, 1992; 2051269; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Translation Notes, 1991; 2051270; 33433116987581 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Translations and Drafts, 1990-1995; 2051275; er.3; 287.6 Kilobytes (7 computer files)
  - Uzbek Research Files, 2050937
    - Ahmad Na’Im Nustratullhbek Interview, 1999; 2051208; er.1; 98.96 Kilobytes (1 computer file)
    - Ayina Index, 2050938; 33433116987532 (Box 16)
    - Central Asian Survey Journal Translation, 1982; 2050943; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and Notes, 1992-1998; 2050944; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Janos Eckman Materials, 1971-1994; 2050945; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Khudayberdiyewa, Halima - Notes and Reserach, 2050946; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Notes and Research Materials, 2050947; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Özbek - English vocabulary notebook vol. I, 1956; 2050948; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Özbek - English vocabulary notebook vol. II, 1956; 2050950; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Özbek - English vocabulary notebook vol. III, 1956; 2050951; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Published Articles, 1982; 2050952; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Translation Reserach, 1998; 2050953; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Turkestan Research, 2050954; 33433116987540 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Turkic Islamic Translations, 2051110; 33433116987557 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Uzbek Language Research, 1997; 2051111; 33433116987557 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Uzbekistan Newspapers and Notes, 1989; 2051112; 33433116987557 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Uzbekistan Newspapers, 1990-1991; 2051113; 33433116987557 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Series V. Miscellany, 1969-1989; 112786; 0.5 boxes
  The miscellany consists of research notes gathered to create bibliographies on Central Asian populations, flyers for conferences on nationality problems in the USSR, and pins related to Crimean Tatar repatriation and an Azerbaijani fraternal society.
  In English and German.
  - Correspondence and materials for bibliography, 1969, 1976; 112787 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Programs on Soviet nationality problems, 1971, 1973, 1977, 1989; 112788 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Fraternal society pins, 112789 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series VI. Sound recordings, 1976, 1989; 112790; 19 audio files
  Consists of sound recordings of an interview and radio programming by Uzbek writer Faizullah Aimaq, aired on Kabul Radio in August 1976; a recording of folk songs sung by the Uighur People's Republic Group; and a series of interviews with Crimean Tatar activist Reshat Djemilev, taped by Edward Allworth in April 1989.
  In English, Russian, and Uzbek.
  - Kabul Radio: Local language programs, 1976 Aug 28; 112791
    Kabul radio, August 28, 1976. Local language programs: Uzbek/Turkmen. Produced by Faizullah Aimaq (recorded by Robert Barrett) Begins with music, followed by interspersed readings of poetry and prose.
    - Side A, 2019919; 208365_f01.mp3; audio file (00:31:29)
    - Side B, 2019920; 208365_f02.mp3; audio file (00:29:48)
  - Kabul Radio: Interview with Faizullah Aimaq and Robert Barrett, 1976 Aug 25; 112792
    Kabul radio, August 25, 1976 Interview with Uzbek writer Faizullah Aimaq and Robert Barrett, and readings by Aimaq. Also includes a tour of Khudayar Khan museum in Kokand, Uzbekistan.
    - Side A, 2020022; 208366_f01.mp3; audio file (00:31:57)
    - Side B, 2020023; 208366_f02.mp3; audio file (00:31:17)
  - Uighur People's Republic Dance Ensemble performance, 1976 Aug 25; 112793
    Performance of the Uighur People's Republic Dance Ensemble at the Kabul Nandare Theater in Kabul, Afghanistan. August 25, 1976. Includes theatrical dialogue, music, folk songs, and a brief narration of the audience members' appearance.
    - Side A, 2020024; 208367_f01.mp3; audio file (00:31:10)
    - Side B, 2020025; 208367_f02.mp3; audio file (00:31:08)
  - Oral History of Reshat Dzhemilev, 1989 Aug 20; 112794
    Oral history recording by Reshat Dzhemilev, a Crimean Tatar dissident from Simferopol, who was deported to Uzbekistan with his family in 1944. He discusses his family history, the 1941 German occupation of Simferopol, his family's deportation, and life in Uzbekistan. Dzhemilev also recalls his life as an activist for a Crimean Tatar homeland, his run-ins with the KGB, trials and imprisonment by the Soviet government. In Russian.
    - Side A, 2020026; 208368_f01.mp3; audio file (00:47:15)
    - Side B, 2020027; 208368_f02.mp3; audio file (00:47:16)
  - Oral History of Reshat Dzhemilev, 1989 Aug 21; 112795
    - Side A, 2020028; 208369_f01.mp3; audio file (00:47:15)
    - Side B, 2020029; 208369_f02.mp3; audio file (00:47:16)
    - Side A, 2020030; 208170_f01.mp3; audio file (00:26:14)
    - Side B, 2020031; 208370_f02.mp3; audio file (00:47:16)
  - Oral History of Reshat Dzhemilev, 112796
    - Side A, 2020036; 208371_f01.mp3; audio file (00:31:31)
    - Side B, 2020037; 208371_f02.mp3; audio file (00:31:30)
    - Side A, 2020038; 208372_f01.mp3; audio file (00:31:30)
    - Side B, 2020039; 208372_f02.mp3; audio file (00:31:31)
    - Side A, 2020040; 208373_f01.mp3; audio file (00:31:27)
    - Side B, 2020041; 208373_f02.mp3; audio file (00:31:28)
    - Side A, 2020042; 208374_f01.mp3; audio file (00:18:57)
  - Interview with Zeki Velidi Togan, 1967; 2051068; origsr.225874; sound recording (unavailable)